A Guide to the April 16, 2007 Community Photograph Collection, 2007-2008
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
April 16, 2007 Community Photograph Collection, 2007-2008
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2013-022
9.0 cu. ft. 15 boxes
A collection of 41 framed photographs having to do with the aftermath of the April 16, 2007 shootings. Photographers were community members who submitted images to be considered for an exhibition at Squires' Perspective Gallery in April 2008. Collection also includes additional digital images not framed for the show.
Each framed image is approximately 20.25 x 16.25 inches.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The April 16, 2007 Community Photograph Collection was transferred to Special Collections from the Perspective Gallery in April 2014.
Custodial History
Framed images were selected by Mary Tartaro from images submitted by the community. The images were first shown in an exhibition in the Perspective Gallery in April 2008. Mary Tartaro was the art director of the gallery at that time. Images were received from Robin Boucher, who was the next art director after Tartaro.
Historical Note
After the April 16, 2007 shootings, the Perspective Gallery of the University Unions and Student Activities put out a call to the community for images relating to the aftermath of this event. From the hundreds of submissions, Mary Tartaro, then art director of the Perspective Gallery, selected 41 images to be framed by Robert Miller for display. These images by more than 25 photographers were first shown in the exhibition "April 16: Remembrance, Recognition, and Healing" from April 5 to 20, 2008. Photographers' statements, expressing their emotions at the time they took them, are included in Box 15.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of 41 framed photographs having to do with the aftermath of the April 16, 2007 shootings. Photographers were community members who submitted images to be considered for an exhibition at Squires' Perspective Gallery in April 2008. The collection also includes additional digital images not framed for the show and statements submitted by photographers.
The "Contents List" below includes a list of the photographs by title. Box 15 includes the names of photographers and the names of the digital files available on CDs in the collection.
Arrangement
Collections is arranged in two series: Series 1, Framed Photographs, includes 41 framed images and the banner from the exhibition with a statement by Zenobia Hikes Series 2, Documentation and Digital Media, includes digital images of most but not all the framed photographs plus additional images submitted by some individuals. It also includes documentation about the exhibition
Framed photographs are in the order received from the gallery. Refer to the excel spreadsheet in Box 15 for information about the framed photographs and corresponding digital files.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Ms2008-020, Virginia Tech April 16, 2007 Archives of the University Libraries, 2007-2010. Finding aid available online.
Ms2013-084, Marching Virginians' April 16, 2007 Condolence Collection, 2007. Finding aid available online.
The April 16, 2007, Condolence Archives online contains more than 7,000 images of materials sent to the university, as well as digital photographs.
Index Terms
Persons:
Baber, Jerry; Browder, Richard; Campbell, Anne Judkins; Criag, Helen; Griffiths, Rick; Hoekzema, Abbey; Holland, Angie; Kline, John; Mahone, Sarah; McCormick, John; Merrey, Caroline; Petersen, Kim; Reid, Jeff; Reid, Kristine; Rich, Miriam; Riggs, Tammy; Solesbee, Jessica; Stanley, Laura; Tartaro, Mary
Genre and Form Terms:
Photographs
Subjects:
April 16, 2007 shootings; University History
Contents List
- Framed Photographs
  - Carnations and mourners (Box 1)
  - Satellite trucks (Box 1)
  - Signing diagonal banners on drillfield (Box 1)
  - Mourners at memorial, April 20, 2007, Maroon & Orange Day (Box 2)
  - Patton Hall with balloons and police cars (Box 2)
  - Pee Wee Pitt Barbecue sign for "Those Remembered" (Box 2)
  - President Charles Steger and Vice President Zenobia Hikes at memorial dedication (Box 3)
  - Man in uniform saluting flags, close-up (Box 3)
  - Sign on Squires doors, "Together We Mourn" (Box 3)
  - Balloons release over Burruss, April 25, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Squires lobby and stairs with condolence items displayed (Box 4)
  - Poster "We are Virginia Tech" with Nikki Giovanni's poem and victims' names (Box 4)
  - Mr. and Mrs. George Bust, Janet Steger, and Gov. Tim Kaine at convocation (Box 5)
  - Graduate mortarboard: "We Will Prevail! VT" (Box 5)
  - Girl on bench with sign "Need Someone to tal to? I will Listen (Free hugs)" (Box 5)
  - Permanent memorial under "midnight blue" sky (Box 6)
  - Norris Hall roped off with memorial in front and VT sign to the right (Box 6)
  - Students at convocation reading April 17, 2007 Collegiate Times headlined "Heartache" (Box 6)
  - Ambulances lined up along Perry Street Lot (Box 7)
  - Aerial view of people standing on the drillfield spelling "VT Thanks You" (Box 7)
  - Memorial outside West Ambler Johnston Hall (Box 7)
  - Burruss with U. S. flag at half staff (Box 8)
  - Blacksburg firefighter watches President Bush's helicopter take off (Box 8)
  - Two cadets at War Memorial Chapel facing altar (Box 8)
  - View of drillfield from memorial with War Memorial Chapel in background (Box 9)
  - Colonial Elementary school students in "VT" formation (Box 9)
  - Football game with Marching Virginians in "VT" formation (Box 9)
  - Mourners hugging with sign, "Free hugs and Hershey Kisses!" (Box 10)
  - White board with signings and one note about 32 Hokies in Heaven (Box 10)
  - Lyric sign, "Our Hearts Are With You VT We Have Hokie Pride" (Box 10)
  - Man writing on white board poem. "When peace like a river..." (Box 11)
  - Backs of older couple hugging on drillfield (Box 11)
  - Entrance to Poor Billy's with ribbon that reads "In Loving Memory" (Box 11)
  - Sign on Squires pointing towards Red Cross Disaster Relief center (Box 12)
  - Ribbons/Prayer flags outside of War Memorial Chapel facing drillfield (Box 12)
  - Overflow crowd in Lane Stadium watching the convocation on the jumbotron (Box 12)
  - Daisies "VT" on grass (Box 13)
  - Collage of signs, "The Roanoke Valley Pays Tribute to Virginia Tech, April 2007" (Box 13)
  - Nighttime vigil, April 17, 2007 (Box 13)
  - Students dancing at Dave Matthews concert (Box 14)
  - NIU memorial vigil, February 18, 2008 (Box 14)
- Banner for exhibition (Box 14)
- Labels from Perspective Gallery, April 16, 2008 Exhibition (print and on CD) (Box-folder 15-1)
- Images selected for framing for Perspective Gallery Show (4 CDs) (Box-folder 15-2)
- Anonymous image (DVD) (Box-folder 15-3)
- John Kline CD (Box-folder 15-4)
- Jeff Reid image CD (Box-folder 15-5)
- Laura Stanlet images on CD (Box-folder 15-6)
- Documentation (Box-folder 15-7)